Preliminary Guide to the John Whitney Hall Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
John Whitney Hall papers
1930-1999
MS 1743
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
4
The papers of John Whitney Hall consist of correspondence and news clippings from his time at Doshisha University, writings, files from the various academic and administrative positions held at the University of Michigan and Yale University, photographs, and files from his work to improve better understandings between the citizens of Japan and the United States. The papers document his life as an undergraduate and his academic and professional career.
Hall, John Whitney, 1916-1997
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Mrs. John W. Hall, 1999.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
John Whitney Hall was born in Tokyo, Japan, on September 23, 1916. He received his A.B. degree from Amherst College in 1939 and a Ph.D. degree from Harvard University in 1950. Following his graduation from Amherst through September 1941 he was an Amherst representative and instructor in English at Doshisha University in Kyoto. He was on the faculty of the University of Michigan from 1948 to 1961 where he also served as director of the Center for Japanese Studies from 1957 to 1960. In 1961 Hall was appointed A. Whitney Griswold Professor of Japanese History at Yale University where he served as chairman of the history department, 1973 to 1976, and of East Asian Languages and Literatures, 1971 to 1974. He was also master of Morse College from 1966 to 1970. In 1983 he retired from Yale. His professional activities included chairmanships of the Japan - United States Friendship Commission, 1976 to 1980, and the United States - Japan Conference on Educational and Cultural Interchange, 1968 to 1980. Hall died on October 21, 1997, in Tucson, Arizona.
Scope and Contents
The papers of John Whitney Hall consist of correspondence and news clippings from his time at Doshisha University, writings, files from the various academic and administrative positions held at the University of Michigan and Yale University, photographs, and files from his work to improve better understandings between the citizens of Japan and the United States. The papers document his life as an undergraduate and his academic and professional career.
Hall, John Whitney, 1916-1997; Japan-United States Friendship Commission; United States-Japan Conference on Cultural and Educational Interchange; University of Michigan. Center for Japanese Studies; Yale University -- Faculty
- Inventory
  - Organizations and conferences concerned with Japanese Studies, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Curriculum vita/bibliographies, undated (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Canadian Academy, 1977, 1996, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Undergraduate papers
    - "Charles Bulfinch and his Boston, 1790-1820", 1991, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - "Emerson and Hindu Thought", undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - "The Japanese Letters of Lafcadio Hearn", undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - "The Reflection in his Poetry of Milton's Knowledge of Music", 1937 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Amherst-Doshisha Representative
    - Doshisha University, 1930, 1952, 1962, 1979-1980, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Amherst House, 1939-1941 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Correspondence, 1939-1947, 1980-1990 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - History of Amherst House, Circa 1941 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Correspondence and news clippings
      - 1939 (Box 1, Folder 12)
      - 1940 Jan-Apr 30 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      - 1940 Apr 30-Aug 9 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      - 1940 Aug 1-Oct (Box 1, Folder 15)
      - 1940 Nov 7-Dec 2 (Box 1, Folder 16)
      - 1940 Dec 3-26 (Box 1, Folder 17)
      - 1940 Nov 28, 1941 Jan 9-Feb 27 (Box 1, Folder 18)
      - 1941 Mar 1-May 28 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      - 1941 Jun 2-Sep 4 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - News clippings regarding conditions in Japan, 1941 March-April (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Woodblock prints designed by John W. Hall, 1939-1941 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Harvard Graduate School, 1941 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - University of Michigan. Center for Japanese Studies Courses, 1953-1960 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - University of Michigan Field Station, Okayama, Japan, 1951-1952 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Letters dictated by John W. Hall to Robin Hall, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Transcribed letters, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Japanese news clippings, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - University of Michigan. Center for Japanese Studies Occasional Papers, 1952-1953 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Newspaper clippings, 1954- 1959 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - University of Michigan. Center for Japanese Studies [fiftieth anniversary], 1997 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Correspondence, 1966-1983 (Box 2, Folder 32)
  - Yale miscellaneous, 1965-1970, 1981-1995 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Committee on Education in the Residential Colleges, 1978 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - East Asian Council, 1971-1972 (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Asakawa, Kan'ichi, 1960s-1990s (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - Griswold/Brewster History Project, 1993 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Conference on Cultural and Educational Interchange, 1962-1993 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Hakone Conference, 1982 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Social Science Research Council--Joint Committee on Japanese Studies
    - 1967-1968 (Box 2, Folder 40)
    - 1969-1970 (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - 1969-1971 (Box 2, Folder 42)
    - 1970-1972 (Box 2, Folder 43)
    - Proposal, 1968-1980 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Efforts to pass "The Japanese-American Friendship Act of 1972", 1970-1976 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Friendship Commission, 1930-1999
    - Membership lists, undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Minutes, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Correspondence
      - 1975-1980 (Box 2, Folder 48)
      - 1976 (Box 2, Folder 49)
    - Meetings
      - 1977 Jan (Box 2, Folder 50)
      - 1977 Mar (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Friendship Fund [requests for general information], 1976 (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Friendship Act [miscellaneous], 1975-1977 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Friendship Commission
    - General Services Administration, 1976 (Box 2, Folder 54)
    - Program, 1972, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 55)
    - Public programs
      - 1980-1988 (Box 3, Folder 56)
      - 1989-1991 (Box 3, Folder 57)
    - Related programs, 1972-1973 (Box 3, Folder 58)
    - Publications, 1989-1999 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Japan-United States Friendship Commission: A History of the Commission Commemorating the 20th Anniversary, 1975-1995 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  - "Japan-United States Friendship Commission: 1975-1995," [draft history by Francis B. Tenny] (Box 3, Folder 61)
  - Correspondence
    - 1982-1986 (Box 3, Folder 62)
    - 1987-1989 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Amherst-Doshisha honorary degree 1976, 1952, 1975-1978 (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Japan-Handbuch, 1975-1982 (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Neesima Lectures, 1983-1988 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - History of Man, 1987-1991 (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Amherst Fiftieth Reunion 1989, 1988-1989 (Box 3, Folder 68)
  - Amherst honorary degree 1989, 1988-1989 (Box 3, Folder 69)
  - Cambridge History of Japan
    - 1977-1981 (Box 3, Folder 70)
    - 1982-1985 (Box 3, Folder 71)
    - 1986-1992 (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Correspondence
    - 1990-1992 (Box 3, Folder 73)
    - 1993-1995 (Box 3, Folder 74)
    - 1996-1998 (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - Awards
    - 1976-1993 (Box 3, Folder 76)
    - 1991-1994 (Box 3, Folder 77)
  - Book reviews, 1991-1994 (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - Writings, undated (Box 3, Folder 79 - 83)
  - Obituaries and memorials, 1997-1998 (Box 3, Folder 84)
  - Maps, undated (Box 3, Folder 85)
  - Correspondence [tributes and letters of sympathy], 1997-1998 (Box 3, Folder 86 - 88)
  - Correspondence [tributes and letters of sympathy], 1997-1998 (Box 4, Folder 89)
  - Unidentified correspondence in Japanese, undated (Box 4, Folder 90)
  - Japan Foundation, 1990-1995 (Box 4, Folder 91)
  - Publications and clippings about Japan, undated (Box 4, Folder 92 - 94)
  - Publications and clippings about Japan, undated (Box 5, Folder 95)
  - Fourth United States-Japan Conference on Cultural and Educational Exchange, 1968 (Box 5, Folder 96)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 5, Folder 97 - 99)